Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Rufus Henry Fitzgerald, Administrative Files, 1945-1955 UA.2.10.1945-1955
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Honorary Degrees, 1910-1945 (Box 24, Folder 199)
  Lists of honorary degrees, 1910-1929 and 1907-1945
- H (General) (Box 24, Folder 200)
  Education Camp Project, 1948 – Samuel Harper – Teaching Resources; Galen C. Hartman – Subscription to building fund; Mrs. Clifford Heinz – miscellaneous possible gift; Mrs. Lois E. Hibernia gave a German Bible to the University which may be in the library; Housing Committee, 1947 – Minutes of the meetings; Correspondence of Ivan G. Nagy of the Hungarian Legation, Rustem Vambery Minister of Hungary; Visiting the Hungarian Room – Mrs. Mitchell's letter, 1947; from diary of R.A. Hall, March 1943; Correspondence: Mrs. Roy Hunt, Mr. and Mrs Clifford Heinz.
- Industry-College Conference, November 12-13, 1953 (Box 24, Folder 201)
  Proceedings of conference held at the Greenbrier, White Sulphur Springs, WV; Correspondence
- International Association of Universities (Box 24, Folder 202)
- I (General) (Box 24, Folder 203)
  Information Please Almanac; Policy for Institutes, special lecture events and short courses.
- J (General) (Box 24, Folder 204)
  John Jenness dissertation; Paneling from B.F. Jones mansion
- K (General) (Box 24, Folder 205)
  KDKA Radio Station – tower near Stadium, 1947; KQV Peache Ground Breaking ceremony, April 24, 1947 – program; A.T. Kearney & Co. – survey of administrative operations (awarded to Cresap); Kerr letter; Chesterfield report controversy.
- School of Law (Box 24, Folder 206)
  Legal education in Pennsylvania (confidential copy no. 36; Dean Arthur Larsen becomes Undersecretary of Labor, 1954
- Institute of Local Government (Box 24, Folder 207)
  Memorandum on the purpose, progress and prospects of, June 1949; Pennsylvania Municipal employees retirement law, a summary, 1949; Duties of the Assistant Directors; Background of the Institute
- Library (Box 25, Folder unknown container)
  Correspondence and Minutes of meeting concerning the policy for the Darlington Library, 1955; Policy for main library (University Librarian or Director of University Libraries); Pamphlet: Personal memories of the Darlington Family at Guyasuta, Anne Hemphill Herbert, 1949; Desire to have a spoken record collection, 1954; Answer concerning the Cresap report on the library
- Loyalty Oath Act (PA), 1949-1953 (Box 25, Folder 209-212)
  Memos and certifications of loyalty for University employees per the requirements of the Act; Herman T. Epstein; materials that Fitzgerald took to Harrisburg, 4/30/1951; Memoranda and correspondence regarding the Oath.
- L (General) (Box 25, Folder 213)
  Lilly correspondence on Bar-Ilan University and Salk Vaccine; Leland Baldwin/Stefan Lorant and the History of Pittsburgh; Lubic Award
- School of Medicine (Box 26, Folder 214)
  Admissions of students reviewed; Financial aid to medical education; Research grant procedures, 1952; Retirement at 70 years of age; Secretaries to receive 3 weeks vacation after working 5 years; Text of Speech by Dr. Jonas Salk, 1950: The importance of identifying polio viruses, 1950; Dedication program of Western State Psychiatric Hospital, 1942; Cornerstone ceremonies of Western State Psychiatric Hospital, 1938; Prospects for Vice Chancellor of Health Professions
- Medical Center (Box 26, Folder 215)
  Presbyterian Hospital agreement, October 14, 1930; Magee Hospital agreement, 1947; Medical Center planning; Picture of group of buildings (photo-file)
- Mellon Institute (Box 26, Folder 216)
  Relationship between the University and Mellon Institute. (Biography of Dr. Edward Ray Weidlein; put in personal file)
- Middle States Association (Box 26, Folder 217)
  List of the Committee; Aims and Purposed of the University (excerpts from the 1787 and 1819 charters; Suggestions made by University of Pittsburgh administrative staff following Middle States 1952 evaluation
- Department of Military Science and Tactics (Box 26, Folder 218)
- M (General) (Box 26, Folder 219)
  Development plan for Panther Hollow submitted by Philip S. Broughton (Mellon Trust); Mental Illness of students; Memorial service for deceased faculty – program, May 22, 1955; May 23, 1954; November 30, 1949; Memorial windows in the old chapel on Northside for Robert Bruce and Dr. Black – wanted to buy them from present owners; Municipal Hospital
- National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis (Box 26, Folder 220)
  "Evaluation of 1954 Field Trial of Poliomyelitis Vaccine, summary report."; "The Scientist Speaks for Himself" CBS Radio, March 26, 1953
- Nationality Rooms (Box 26, Folder 221)
  Old Pennsylvania furniture given by Max Vance (Pittsburgh Plate Glass Co.), Was from Andrew Vance house in Frankfort Springs; German Class Room, presentation of Fairy Tale window 1954; Mrs. Ruth Crawford Mitchell – letters (hand written); Formal dedication of the Italian Room – program, 1949; Christmas Dinner program
- Nationality Rooms, English Classroom (Box 26, Folder 222)
  Blueprint of the room; List of medallions for windows; Correspondence with and photograph of Sir Alfred C. Bossom; List of books locked in the English Room, two dispatch boxes and facsimiles of the Magna Carta Great Seal of King John; Program of dinner at 20th Century Club given by 18 Committees for Dr. and Mrs. Fitzgerald; Citation for Doctor of Laws degree awarded Alfred Charles Bossom (on back of program); List of invitations sent; Speeches given; Pictures of the room as dedicated
- New York University (Box 26, Folder 223)
  Root-Tilden Scholarships
- Daybooks, March 1, 1938-June 30, 1955 (Box 27-34, Folder 224-231)
  No restrictions. Box 28 FF 225 has an envelope marked as restricted access.
  These files contain the notes, memoranda and transcripts of meetings and telephone conversations of Fitzgerald from the time he was Provost until he retired as Chancellor in June 1955.
  Arrangement
  The Daybooks are arranged by date.
- Nuclear Research, 1946 (Box 35, Folder 232)
  Memo on Regional Laboratory for Nuclear Research involving Pitt, Tech and Westinghouse, Meeting at Carnegie Institute of Technology, July 26, 1946
- Nurses Residence (Box 35, Folder 233)
  Dedication invitation, May 11, 1953; Dr. Fitzgerald's remarks; Herbert M. Garland, Director
- School of Nursing, 1939-1954 (Box 35, Folder 234)
  Industrial nursing program not to be discontinued – letters in support of the program; Recommendations for nursing education in the Medical Center; Future plans for the School of Nursing in a letter to Mr. Scaife; 1939, setting-up School of Nursing
- N (General) (Box 35, Folder 235)
  National Advisory Committee on Education; National Association of Deans of Women; National Committee Against Discrimination; National Geographic Society; Ethebert Nevin
- O (General) (Box 35, Folder 236)
  Orr, Overload policy; Owens; Open House
- Pennsylvania Association of Colleges and Universities (Box 35, Folder 237)
- Commonwealth of Pennsylvania (Box 35, Folder 238)
- Personnel Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 35, Folder 239)
  Minutes and Correspondence
- Physical Plant (Box 35, Folder 240)
  List of projected work; Ellsworth building; Report of Survey of Dental Infirmary, 1954; Furnishing of the 12th floor of the Cathedral of Learning by Mrs. Heinz; Report of Survey of Thaw Hall, 1954; William G. Fisher, Director
- School of Pharmacy (Box 35, Folder 241)
  Borden Scholarship Award, 1954, 1954, etc.; In 1098, the Scio College of Pharmacy became an affiliate of the University and was called the Pittsburgh College of Pharmacy. On January 26, 1948 the merger was completed and it became the University of Pittsburgh, School of Pharmacy
- Phi Beta Kappa (Box 35, Folder 242)
  Constitution and bylaws, 1949 (general); Bylaws of XI Chapter of the University of Pittsburgh; Extracts from college catalogs with respect to counting vocational courses toward liberal arts courses
- Pitcairn-Crabbe Foundation Lectures (Box 35, Folder 243)
  Correspondence; Programs; Invitations; Chancellor Bowman given honorary degree, 1948
- Pittsburgh Photographic Library, 1954-1955 (Box 35, Folder 244)
- Psychiatric Cases (Box 35, Folder 245)
  Committee formed to address students with mental health problems
- Graduate School of Public Health (Box 35, Folder 246)
  Proposal for conferring of additional degrees, 1955; Institute on Hospital Affairs suggested; Progress Report, 1948-1952; Clippings on the possible purchase of Municipal Hospital; Outline of memorandum relative to the possibility of establishing a Graduate School of Public Health; see also FF 390-399
- Department of Public Instruction (Box 35, Folder 247)
  Courses approved, 1955; Report of higher institutions of learning, 1953/54; Biennial Report, 1952/54; Report, 1952/53; Report 1951/52; Biennial report 1950/52; Report 1950/51; Report 1949/50; Biennial report, 1948/50
- Public Relations Counselor (Box 36, Folder 248)
  Library Study Committee report on space problems, Francis C. Pray; Faculty Schedule Card; Scholarship information
- P (General) (Box 36, Folder 249)
  Paintings (description of portrait of Sabina Wolfe Brackenridge by Rembrandt Peale and Hugh Henry Brackenridge); Patent policy, by Senate Committee; "Ex Hoc Semine Nostra Gloria", by John Milton Duff, M.D. (reprint given by Harriet Duff Phillips); Plaque for original site of Pittsburgh Academy Log cabin; Pittsburgh Child Guidance Center
- Registrar (Box 36, Folder 250)
  Enrollment, divided in several ways, 1952/53, 1953/54, 1954/55; Enrollment records by schools 1940/41-1950/51; Letter from Registrar to Chancellor about Cresap Report on the office functions; Student enrollment, 1929/30 – 1948/49; Bujno, Bruno
- Religion-in-life Conference, 1951-1955 (Box 36, Folder 251)
- Research Bureau for Retail Training (Box 36, Folder 252)
  Correspondence concerning degrees; Testimonial dinner honoring Professor Bishop Brown, 1949 (program and speech)
- Research, 1938-1944 (Box 36, Folder 253, Othertype 1-3)
  Research project in chemistry, physics, biology, and psychology progress report to the Buhl Foundation, 1942; Proposal for an expanded program of research on metals; Special report to the Buhl Foundation…on research on war emergency problems, 1942; Minutes of the meeting of the Research Committee, May 11, 1942; Special report to the Buhl Foundation relative to problems raised by national defense activities; Nine pamphlets of reprints of research projects; Correspondence with Dr. Charles G. King; John and Mary R. Markle Foundation for research in biochemistry; Budget plan; Proposed budget 1941/42 – 1945/46; A proposal for establishing a science research division at the University of Pittsburgh; Experiments with direct currents on chick embryos, by Peter Gray, 1939; Some thoughts on the Pittsburgh cyclotron; Report on the Proposed University of Pittsburgh cyclotron; Many reports to the Buhl Foundation on progress of science research
- Research in the Natural Sciences, 1952-1955 (Box 37, Folder 254)
  Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, National Science Foundation; Clapp Hall space; Correspondence with Longenecker; Buhl Foundation; Gulf Research cooperative plan; patents
- Retirement (Box 37, Folder 255)
  Lists and dates for those retired (medallions sent); correspondence; Proposed retirement and annuity plan
- R (General) (Box 37, Folder 256)
- Seismological Laboratory (Box 37, Folder 257)
  Donation of Dr. George H. Clapp, 1938; In the Cathedral of Learning
- Senate, 1941-1943 (Box 37, Folder 258)
  Minutes of the Executive Committee; Report of the Committee on budget policies to the Senate, 1943; Membership lists; Report of the University Senate Committee on membership; Constitution of the University Senate, adopted by the Temporary University Council at January 3, 1941
- Senate, 1943-1955 (Box 37, Folder 259)
  Constitution Committee, 1955; Committee reports, 1953/54; Recommendations approved by Senate, May 15, 1953; Notes concerning its establishment; Annual report of the secretary May 12, 1944
- Temporary University Council, 1938-1941 (Box 37, Folder 260)
  To set up University Senate; Constitution of the University Senate, January 3, 1941; Minutes of meetings, 1940-41; Correspondence concerning the planning of a University Senate; University Council, 1935 (under Chancellor Bowman)
- Senate, Committee on Athletics (Box 37, Folder 261)
  New Committee according to Trustees new policy; Recommendations for varsity letter awards; Civic Light Opera to use Stadium; Outline of athletic scheduling and budget procedure, April 18, 1947; Committee resolutions
- Senate, Committee on Budget Policies (Box 37, Folder 262)
  Report to the Senate by the Educational Policies Committee, February 16, 1951; Other reports of committee, 1950; Report on "overload"
- Senate, Committee on Constitution of the Senate (Box 37, Folder 263)
  Study of the constitution, May 1955
- Senate, Educational Policies Committee, July 1952-February 1955 (Box 37, Folder 264)
  Report, November 1954; First progress report, 1953-54; Resolutions of the Committee, May 1953; Report, 1952/53 & 1951-53; Notes on a proposed faculty charter, January, 1953; Statement, May 1952
- Senate, Educational Policies Committee (Box 37, Folder 265)
  Proposal for making awards to members of our faculty to stimulate scholarly projects and better teaching; Statement of the committee, May 9, 1952; Statement on policy concerning faculty obligations and teaching loads, 1948; Report, August 1945; and 1943
- Senate, Educational Policies Committee, Humanities, Natural Sciences, and Social Sciences Reports (Box 37, Folder 266)
- Senate, Committee on Elections, 1942-1945 (Box 37, Folder 267)
- Senate, Executive Committee, Minutes, 1943-1955 (Box 37, Folder 268)
- Senate, Faculty Welfare Committee (Box 37, Folder 269)
  Reports on T.I.I.A.; Group Medical and Surgical Insurance; Joint Housing Project
- Senate, Library and University Publications Committee (Box 37, Folder 270)
  Various reports on the condition of the library; Consideration given for a Friends of the Library group; Plans for a Science-Technology Library
- Senate, Public Relations Committee (Box 37, Folder 271)
  Committee meetings, 1952, 1950, 1946, 1943, 1942
- Senate, Publications Committee (Box 37, Folder 272)
  Meetings and Reports
- Senate, Committee on Registration Procedure (Box 37, Folder 273)
- Senate, Retirement Policy Committee (Box 37, Folder 274)
  Correspondence, Memoranda 1943-1946
- Senate, Student Relations Committee, 1942-1953 (Box 39, Folder 275)
- Senate, Tenure and Academic Freedom Committee (Box 39, Folder 276)
  Organized February 1942; Committee reports to 1955
- Senior Memorials (Box 39, Folder 277)
  Heinz Chapel windows
- Sequoia Trees, 1955 (Box 39, Folder 278)
  Plans for planting. History of the tree, 1955
- Shiftwork Courses, 1941-1942 (Box 39, Folder 279)
  Program to accommodate students who work changing shifts
- School of Social Work (Box 39, Folder 280, Volume 1-2)
  Buhl Foundation grant, 1954; Memos – Social Work alumni; Letters from alumni upholding the Dean's stand; Freedom of speech upheld; Controversy over Dr. Hathaway; Freedom of speech and tenure
- Space Research Coordination Center (Box 40, Folder 281-284)
  These folders have been relocated to UA RG 15/19. They contain the correspondence and memoribila from the development of the SRCC.
- Special Services (Box 40, Folder 285)
  Surplus properties; List of special activities of Viers W. Adams, Director, 1952-53
- Stadium (Box 40, Folder 286)
  Bonds and bondholders
- Student Health Service (Box 40, Folder 287)
  "Minute a Day" program for by H C Carlson; "Social Fundamentals"
- Student Organizations (Box 40, Folder 288)
  Student Faculty Organization Social rules; Information concerning student activities or off-campus engagements
- Scholarships Not Awarded (Box 40, Folder 289)
  Applications not granted, 1949-1950; Received scholarship from other sources; Request for scholarship withdrawn; Scholarships not recommended by Deans; RHF did not approve the scholarships recommended for these students
- Special Scholarships, 1946-1951 (Box 40, Folder 290)
  University scholarships, 1951/52 – 1946/47; Memo on Senatorial scholarships
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], 1951/52 (Box 40, Folder 291)
  List of those receiving Scholarships, 1951/52; application papers and grades for each person
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], Summer 1948-1950/51 (Box 41, Folder 292-294)
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], 1945/46-1947/48 (Box 42, Folder 295-297)
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], 1942/43-1944/45 (Box 43, Folder 298-300)
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], 1939/40-1941/42 (Box 44, Folder 301-303)
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], 1938/39 (Box 45, Folder 304)
- Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships [RESTRICTED], Summer 1938 and 1941/42 list (Box 45, Folder 305)
- S (General) (Box 45, Folder 306)
  Alfred Bossom's letter; Senatorial scholarships; Scharfe, Howard C. – Biography; Proposed Division of research of Social Sciences; Use of Soldiers and Sailors Memorial Hall; Leopold Stokowski correspondence; Symposium on Combustion, 1954; Correspondence: Schaefer, Salchli, Schenley Apartments Co. re: Thackery, Schinneller; Schmidt, A.W., Spanish Embassy, Stokowski Leopold (with Signature),
- Statement of Principles for the Medical Center (Box 46, Folder 307)
  Duties of the Vice-chancellor for Health Professions; Plans for the development of the Health Center
- Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association (TIAA) (Box 46, Folder 308)
- Temple University (Box 46, Folder 309)
  Correspondence concerning acceleration for superior high school students
- Tenure (Box 46, Folder 310)
  University of Pittsburgh Tenure plan, February 1949; plans of other schools
- Treasurer (Box 46, Folder 311)
  Office hours, vacations; Memo on workmen-compensation insurance; Life insurance plan, July 1, 1945; Receipts and expenditures for the Buhl Foundation grant for School of Applied Social Sciences, 1942/43; Research Fund in biochemistry, 1941/42
- T (General) (Box 46, Folder 312)
  Correspondence with Taylor re: Edward Elgar; Texas Universities; Theological Seminaries; Thirteen Citizens Committee; Tilden Scholarship; Turner
- Tuition Allowances, 1953-1955 (Box 46, Folder 313)
  Policy, correspondence and chart
- Tuition and Fees (Box 46, Folder 314)
  Fees: physical education, Applied social sciences, Research Bureau for Retail Training; Tuition increase
- U.S. Department of the Navy (Box 46, Folder 315)
  Trainee work; Plaque given in appreciation for World War II co-operation, 1947; Peacetime education of Naval Officers; Exchange of professors; Charles McKenna Lynch retires as Director of Naval Officers procurement – 4th Naval District, 1945
- U.S. Office of Education (Department of Health, Education and Welfare), 1943-1955 (Box 46, Folder 316)
  Study of college students retention and withdrawal, 1953; Education directory, 1952/53; correspondence during war years; Ruth Crawford Mitchell, "The Nationality Rooms at the University of Pittsburgh and international understanding"
- University Car (Box 46, Folder 317)
- University Invitations, 1954-1955 (Box 47, Folder 318)
  Academic celebrations that the University was invited to attend.
- University Press, 1947-1955 (Box 47, Folder 319)
  Invitation: Regional awards in history to Dr. Charles Fletcher Lewis, Director of the Buhl Foundation and to George Mercer Papers, relating to the Ohio Company of Virginia, comp. and e. by Lois Mulkearn; clipping: 5 women run the University Press at Pitt (short history of); 1954; clipping: Mary E. Bakewell – "Of long ago"; A few catalogs; A Series of books on historic western Pennsylvania
- University Research Committee, 1951 (Box 47, Folder 320)
  Memos on ideas for research policies and contracts; Procedures relating to research financed by individuals and organizations outside the University, 1951
- U (General) and U.S. Air Force (Box 47, Folder 321)
  House Un-American Activities Committee; U.S. Army; U.S. Air Force; Map making; International Relations; U.S. Attorney General; U.S. Civil Service; U.S. Congress; School of Medicine, Committee on Research and Development Report
- U. S. Government (Box 47, Folder 322)
  Department of Interior. Bureau of Reclamation. Demineralization of saline waters. October 1952 66 p.; ROTC; Education and Labor; Marine Corps; Post Office (propaganda); Dept. of State; Treasury; University Food Service
- Veterans, 1952 (Box 47, Folder s324)
  Senatorial scholarships for Korean Veterans, 1952; Emergency Committee for amendment of Korean G.I. bill, 1952
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of the Health Professions (Moore), July 1954-June 1955 (Box 47, Folder 324)
  Letters concerning more budgetary needs, 1955; Policy on patents; Policy for Health Professions Libraries, 1955
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of the Health Professions (Moore), January-June 1954 (Box 47, Folder 325)
  Pension plan, 1954; plans for Health Professions building, 1955; List of nine policies, 1954; Falk Clinic board; Council of Deans meeting, January 15, 1954
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of the Health Professions (Moore), Falk Clinic, 1937-1949 (Box 47, Folder 325a)
  Includes Annual Reports for Falk Clinic, 1947-48 and 1952-53
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of the Health Professions (Moore), September -December 1953 (Box 48, Folder 326)
  Letter in connection with developing a Medical Center in Oakland; Planning the Nurses' Residence building; "The Tower" Autumn 1953; Dinner in honor of Dr. Robert Moore; "This I believe" – speech of Dr. Moore at the dinner; General policies of the School of Health Professions
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of the Health Professions, 1952-1953 (Box 48, Folder 327)
  Vice Chancellor search
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of the Health Professions, December 1952-September 1953 (Box 48, Folder 328)
  Outline of program for development of Medical Center as submitted by Mr. Falk at the meeting of the Board of Trustees, held on 9/18/1953
- Schools of the Health Professions (Box 48, Folder 329)
  Policies
- Vice Chancellor, Schools of Health Professions (Box 49, Folder 330)
  Search for 10/15/1951 to January 1952; Speech of Dr. A. LeRoy Johnson given to RHF by Dr. Alan Gregg, "Between two mountains of conceit"; "The golden gate of medicine", by Alan Gregg, M.D. Vitae of candidates
- Vice Chancellor (Charles B. Nutting), February 1952-June 1955 (Box 49, Folder 331)
  "Living abroad at home"; an international curricula-Community Program for undergraduate students, prepared by Mrs. Ruth Crawford Mitchell, October 25, 1954, 13 pages; Dr. Fitzgerald advised to send to Rockefeller Foundation; Memo on procedure for appointment; Duties of the Vice-Chancellor; "The framework of freedom", by Charles B. Nutting; clippings of Dean of Law School Nutting appointed Vice-Chancellor
- V (General) (Box 49, Folder 332)
  "The significance of the Pittsburgh story", address by Arthur B. Van Buskirk 12 pages; Vaughn and Van Bremer correspondence
- War Emergency (1) (Box 49, Folder 333)
  Memos; pamphlets; Office of War Information "victory"; Proclamation for fifth registration day (for War); Air raid instructions; Minutes of Deans' meeting, February 2, 1942; and January 5, 1942; Deferment of students, 1941; Directory of War Agencies
- War Emergency (2) (Box 50, Folder 334)
  Pamphlets on war training; "Classification and selection"; Engineering Defense Program; Vocational training; ROTC; Civil Aeronautics Authority; Organizational chart of the Defense Training Personnel; Research work being done
- War Emergency, R.A. Gilmore, November 1942-April 1944 (Box 50, Folder 335)
- War Emergency, Air R.O.T.C., 1945-1946 (Box 50, Folder 336)